<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Dr. Eng. Frederick N. Numbisi</title>
    <link>https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Dr. Eng. Frederick N. Numbisi</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 11:14:48 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Project 7: Mapping Arid vegetation communities and habitats</title>
      <link>https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/post/project-7/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 11:14:48 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/post/project-7/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Information on vegetation assemblage and habitat mapping were sourced from three main streams: 1. Inventory data collected during field surveys, 2. Estimated proxies for vegetation structure and phenology – vegetation indices, and 3. Estimates of spectral signatures for ground features from time-series remote sensing imagery.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;To map the vegetation assemblages and habitats, the random forest classification algorithm was implemented to delineate clusters of vegetation types, hitherto identified and grouped as clusters of plant assemblages.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Field referenced points and polygons for the vegetation assemblages were used to extract training data from the stack of engineered spatial features (10 explanatory or predictor raster layers).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In selecting a reliable classifier algorithm for the considered vegetation community or habitat types, a Multi-Classifier System (MCS) of algorithms that comprise ensemble modelling, bagging, and boosting: Random Forest ensemble decision tree (RF), Support Vector Machine (SVM), Regularized discriminant analysis (RDA) model, Naïve Bayes classifier (NB), and the Gradient Boosting Model (GBM). All model training was implemented using the “caret” library in R program.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The RF classification algorithm had better performance (overall accuracy and kappa statistics) and was applied to model the spatial location and distribution of the reference classes from field inventory (clusters of vegetation assemblages and communities) and the available spatial (raster image) predictors.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Optimised the RF classifier algorithms using forward feature selection (Meyer et. al., 2018) and spatial cross-validation procedure to reach the best model.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A Leave-Location-Out Cross Validation (LLO-CV) was applied to address potential class selection bias and overfitting, and a resampling control of 10-fold cross-validation with 5 iterations.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The RF model training and cross validation was implemented within the “CAST” library (Meyer et al., 2023) of the R statistical program.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/images/Project_SpatialAnalysisGrid.png&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;h4&gt;Arid Plant Communities Classifier Grid&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/images/AlUla_ClassificationModelsKappa.png&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;h4&gt;Class Prediction Accuracy compared for classifier models&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/images/VegetaionCommunitiesMap.png&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;h4&gt;Vegetation communities and habitat map&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/images/VegModel_MapBwithAOA.png&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;h4&gt;Vegetation communities and habitat map with consideration of Area of Applicability (AOA) of classification model&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Project 6: Predictor of Important Arid plants hotspots</title>
      <link>https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/post/project-6/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2023 14:05:58 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/post/project-6/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Create a Raster Grid for the Area of Interest (AOI) or study area.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The raster grid is sub-divided in quared grids of desired size or analysis resolution. For instance, into 2km by 2km grid sizes.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Labelling each 2km square grid and creating uniqur Cell IDs (for each grid) for tracking the species distribution across grids.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Use information on actual species distribution (point coordinates of observed presence) to cross-correlated inferred species distribution from literature and expert knowledge.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Apply threshold criteria for area of inferred distribution polygons intersecting the grids of observed presence to classify grids for the target species distribution.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Develop species distribution hotspot grids following IUCN threshold criteria i.e. Endemic species, Threatened speacies, etc.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/images/SoqGrid1_Baleria_popovii.png&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;h4&gt;Important Plant Area (IPA) Study Area Grid&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/images/SoqGrid2_Baleria_popovii.png&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;h4&gt;Species Distribution Analysis Grid&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/images/SoqGrid3_Baleria_popovii.png&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;h4&gt;Target Species Grid Classification&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/images/InferredDistribution91Species1.png&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;h4&gt;Distribution Hotspot Grid for Threatened Endemic Species&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Project 5: Predictor of Plant distribution clusters</title>
      <link>https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/post/project-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2023 11:25:05 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/post/project-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;As a proxy for vegetation photosynthetic activity, vegetation indices (VIs) were estimated from the visible to near-infrared, i.e. VIS-NIR, spectral bands from remote sensing images.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Sentinel-2 Level-2A (S-2A) images we collected using the Google Earth Engine (GEE) cloud computing platform. For now, we have considered scenes within the period from January to December 2021 without cloud filtering. The clouds were later masked and the images co-registered as image collections.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In an exploratory analysis of vegetation cover, 5 different vegetation indices (VIs) were computed and stacked for processing and analysis.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;As no ground truth data is yet available for the period of exploratory analysis (2021), we applied an unsupervised image classification procedure was applied.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;This classification experiment hypothesised a combination of VIs to provide complementary information and features to enhance thresholding of vegetation and land cover types. Nonetheless, for VI-based classification, it is inappropriate to assume similar vegetation class thresholds for all VI types - the widely applied thresholds may not be optimal for all VIs, vegetation types and context.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The K-means clustering algorithm was applied with 5 clusters selected based on visual observations from the classes obtained by VI thresholding.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;On this basis clustering results, we applied five thresholds of potential vegetation classes (&amp;lt; 0.2:  No Vegetation, 0.2 – 0.3: Low vegetation, 0.3 – 0.4: Sparse vegetation, 0.4 – 0.5: Moderate vegetation, and &amp;gt; 0.5: Moderate-High vegetation).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Image thresholding procedure and unsupervised classification (image clustering) were conducted using the GEE cloud computing platform and the resultant images exported as Geo Tiff files for further (supervised) analysis.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/images/KMeans_ElbowPlot_SilhouetteMetric.png&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;h4&gt;K-Means Clustering Silhoutte Metric&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/images/DAFORSpecies_HCA_Dendrogram_ClustersLabeled.png&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;h4&gt;Heirarchical Cluster Analysis Dendrogram&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/images/DAFORspecies_HCA_JaccardSimilarityIndexPlot.png&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;h4&gt;Jaccard Similarity Index Analysis of Clusters&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/images/AsharVIthresholdClasses.png&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;h4&gt;Vegetation cover classes for Wadi Ashar according to thresholds of different vegetation indices (VIs): a. NDVI b. EVI, c. SAVI, d. MSAVI, and e. GSAVI&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/images/AsharKmeanClustersVegClasses.png&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;h4&gt;The vegetation classes from unsupervised (K-means clustering) classification of time-series images of 5 VIs&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Project 4: Forest (and Tree) Cover Loss from 2001-2021 in Cashew production regions</title>
      <link>https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/post/project-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jul 2022 20:20:48 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/post/project-4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An analysis of trends in Tree and Forest Cover change in cashew production (the project) areas covering three agro-ecological zones.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ivory Coast (CDI) is ranked second global producer of cashew nuts, behind India. In CDI, cashew production contributes an important proportion (1.3%) of national GDP (FAO 2018) and to the livelihood of an important number of small-scale farmers.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;However, increasing production of cashew is strongly tied to increases in the production land (Figure 1). Cashew production is carried out in about 19 (of the 33) regions in CDI (Bassett et. al. 2018) and predominantly in the Sudan and Sudano-Guinean agro-ecological zones (FAO 2018), which are largely characterised as fragile ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Project 3: Estimator of Tree Spatial Pattern in Agroforests</title>
      <link>https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/post/project-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Apr 2021 11:13:32 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/post/project-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Assessed the temporal changes in shade management and spatial dynamics in canopy tree structure and live tree biomass.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Conducted field survey along an age gradient of “family farms” in cocoa agroforests created from forest (fCAFS) and savannah (sCAFS) land cover.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Evaluated the temporal changes in farm structure, relative tree abundance, and live aboveground biomass of the major canopy (shade tree) strata.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Used spatial point process and linear mixed effect analyses to assess contributions of associated perennial trees (AsT) on farm rejuvenation patterns.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Provided insights into farmers’ temporal allocation of uses and prioritization of different tree species associations with age of cocoa agroforests.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Developed recommendations for landscape-specific tree management and considerations in proposing on-farm tree conservation incentives.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/images/SustainabilityFig2.png&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;h4&gt;Spatial sampling and point pattern analysis steps&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/images/SustainabilityFig9.png&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;h4&gt;Spatial pattern of cocoa trees across farm type and age gradients&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Project 2: Cocoa Agroforestry Canopy Gap Predictor</title>
      <link>https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/post/project-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2020 11:00:59 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/post/project-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Estimated canopy cover distribution using in-situ digital hemispherical photographs (DHPs) sampling and estimates of canopy gap fraction.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Built neural network and random forest regression models of cocoa agroforestry canopy gap fraction and Sentinel-1A SAR backscatter intensity and features.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Developed a combination of different backscatter variables for predicting the canopy gap variability in agroforestry cocoa production landscapes.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Utilise a semi-variogram analysis of canopy gap distribution and spatial clustering distances in different cocoa production landscapes.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Provided new insights into the scale of spatial variability of canopy gaps in relation to farm and landscape management through cocoa agroforestry land use.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Built a proof-of-concept to support development of management tools or strategies on tree inventorying and decisions regarding incentives for shade tree retention and planting in cocoa landscapes.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/images/DHPprofile_pictures.png&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;h4&gt;Inventory of canopy cover distribution (ground truth)&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/images/DHP_graphicAbstract.png&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;h4&gt;Field and spatial data analysis workflow&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Frederick-Numbisi/AgroforestryCanopyGapPrediction&#34;&gt;Link to GitHub Repository&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.3390/rs12244163&#34;&gt;Link to Reference Scientifica Publication - 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Project 1: Cocoa Agroforestry Land Use Classifier</title>
      <link>https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/post/project-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Apr 2018 10:58:08 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/post/project-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Developed a classifier procedure for discriminating perennial cocoa agroforestry land cover.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Compared a multi-spectral optical image from RapidEye, acquired in the dry season, and multi-seasonal C-band SAR of Sentinel 1.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Hand engineered Grey Level Co-occurrence Matrix (GLCM) texture features (images) from Sentinel-1 Image time series covering six dry and four wet seasons from 2015 to 2017.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Optimised Random Forest Ensemble classifier models using different input feature combinations; multi-spectral reflectance, vegetation indices, co-(VV) and cross-(VH) polarised SAR intensity and GLCM texture measures.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Evaluated accuracy metrics and uncertainty Shannon entropy - information loss in classification.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Built a classifier and uncertainty measures that provide reliable validation of class discrimination at different spatial resolution.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/images/Figure_3_IJGI_NumbisiFN.png&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;h4&gt;SAR Backscatter Time-series over different land uses&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/images/Figure_8_IJGI_NumbisiFN.png&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;h4&gt;Sentinel-1 SAR GLCM Texture-Based Discrimination of Cocoa Agroforestry land use&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gohugo-theme-ananke.pages.dev/images/Figure_6_IJGI_NumbisiFN.png&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;      &lt;h4&gt;Land use classification compared for Sentinel-1 SAR and Rapid-Eye&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
